<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="AboutDoc">
  <title>About this document</title>

  <para>This document is the user manual for WinMerge 2.8. It explains the capabilities and limitations of WinMerge. This manual is recommended reading for both new and experienced users.</para>

  <para>To learn essential WinMerge basics, please read the following topics:</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="QuickStart">Quick start</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Gets you quickly started with WinMerge and shows its basic usage.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="CompareDirs">Comparing folders</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Explains the folder comparison window, available operations, and customizing the results display.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="CompareFiles">Comparing files</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Explains the file comparison/merge window, available operations, methods of navigation, and modes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="Configuration">Options and configuration</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Explains how to customize WinMerge, including handling whitespace, colours, and text encoding.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>To learn to use WinMerge more efficiently, read these topics:</para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="OpenPaths">Opening files and folders</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Introduces several ways to open files and folders in WinMerge - there are many! For example, do you know how to use the Shell Extension context menu in advanced mode?</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="Plugins">Plugins</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Describes the optional, extra features that you can add to WinMerge using its plugin mechanism.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="Filters">Filters</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Explains how to control what is compared in the folder or file comparison window.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="CommandLine">Commandline</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Lists command-line parameters for using WinMerge with other tools or from a script.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><link linkend="Faq">FAQ</link></term>

      <listitem>
        <para>Contains answers to many common questions asked of developers.</para>

        <para>Before submitting questions to <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/winmerge/">SourceForge.net</ulink>, please check the FAQ first to see if your question is answered there.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</article>
