<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="AboutDoc">
  <title>About This Document</title>

  <para>This is a manual for WinMerge 2.5.</para>

  <para>This manual is important reading for experienced and new users of
  WinMerge 2.5. There are lot of new features and improvements in version 2.5.
  Reading this manual will help ensure the user knows about the various
  functions available in WinMerge, and various limitations.</para>

  <para>Please read at least the following chapters:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="QuickStart">Quick start</link> chapter will get you
      quickly started with WinMerge. After reading this chapter you will know the
      basic usage of WinMerge.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="CompareDirs">Comparing Folders</link> chapter
      explains folder comparison, ways to change the results display, and
      operations available in the folder comparison window.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="CompareFiles">Comparing Files</link> chapter
      explains the file comparison/merge window, its various panes, and methods of
      navigation, modes, and operations available in this window.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="Configuration">Options and Configuration</link>
      chapter helps to customize WinMerge to your needs, including things such as
      whitespace handling, colors, and handling text encoding.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The following chapters are suggested reading for more efficient use of
  WinMerge:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="OpenPaths">Opening Files and Folders</link> chapter
      introduces several ways (there are many!) to open files and folders to
      WinMerge. For example, do you know how to use the Shell Extension context
      menu in advanced mode?</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="Plugins">Plugins</link> chapter introduces
      plugins.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="Filters">Filters</link> chapter explains the use of
      both file filters and line filters.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="CommandLine">Commandline</link> chapter lists
      commandline parameters for WinMerge (for using with other tools, or from a
      script).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The <link linkend="Faq">FAQ chapter</link> contains answers to many
      common questions asked of developers. Please check first if your question is
      answered there before submitting questions to <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/winmerge/">SourceForge.net</ulink>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>
