<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="Command_line">
  <title>Command line<indexterm>
      <primary>command line</primary>
    </indexterm><indexterm>
      <primary>WinMerge command line</primary>

      <see>command line</see>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>The WinMerge command line accepts several parameters in addition to the
  paths to compare. Most of these parameters are intended for using WinMerge as
  an external compare application or starting a compare operation from a batch
  file.</para>

  <para>Use one of these formats for the WinMerge command:</para>

  <para><cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>WinMergeU</command>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/?</option></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis></para>

  <para><cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>WinMergeU</command>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/r</option></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/e</option></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/f</option>
      <replaceable>filter</replaceable></arg>

      <arg><option>/x</option></arg>

      <arg><option>/xq</option></arg>

      <arg><option>/s</option></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/ul</option></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/ur</option></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/u</option></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/wl</option></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/wr</option></arg>

      <arg><option>/minimize</option></arg>

      <arg><option>/maximize</option></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/dl</option>
      <replaceable>leftdesc</replaceable></arg>

      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><option>/dr</option>
      <replaceable>rightdesc</replaceable></arg>

      <arg choice="plain"
      rep="norepeat"><replaceable>leftpath</replaceable></arg>

      <arg choice="plain"
      rep="norepeat"><replaceable>rightpath</replaceable></arg>

      <arg choice="opt"
      rep="norepeat"><replaceable>outputpath</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis></para>

  <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
    <command>WinMergeU</command>

    <arg choice="plain"
    rep="norepeat"><replaceable>conflictfile</replaceable></arg>
  </cmdsynopsis>

  <para>Entering the command with no parameters or pathnames simply opens the
  WinMerge window. Parameters are prefixed with either a forward slash (
  <literal>/</literal> ) or dash ( <literal>-</literal> ) character. Pathnames
  have no prefix character.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><option>/?</option> opens WinMerge Help at this topic.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>recursive folder compare</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option>/r</option> compares all files in all subfolders (recursive
      compare). Unique folders (occurring only on one side) are listed in the
      compare result as separate items. Note that including subfolders can
      increase compare time significantly. Without this parameter, WinMerge
      lists only files and subfolders at the top level of the two target
      folders. It does not compare the subfolders.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>WinMerge window</primary>

        <secondary>closing</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option>/e</option> enables you to close WinMerge with a single
      <keycap>Esc</keycap> key press. This is useful when you use WinMerge as an
      external compare application: you can close WinMerge quickly, like a
      dialog. Without this parameter, you might have to press
      <keycap>Esc</keycap> multiple times to close all its windows.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>filters</primary>

        <secondary>applying in command line</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option>/f</option> applies a specified filter to restrict the
      comparison. The filter can be a filemask like <filename><userinput>*.h
      *.cpp</userinput></filename>, or the name of a file filter like
      <userinput>XML/HTML Devel</userinput>. Add quotation marks around a filter
      mask or name that contains spaces.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option>/x</option> closes WinMerge (after displaying an information
      dialog) when you start a comparison of identical files. The parameter has
      no effect after the comparison, for example if the files become identical
      as a result of merging or editing. This parameter is useful when you use
      WinMerge as an external compare application, or when you want to eliminate
      unnecessary steps by ignoring files that don't have any
      differences.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option>/xq</option> is similar to <option>/x</option> but does not
      show the message about identical files. </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>WinMerge window</primary>

        <secondary>limiting instances</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option>/s</option> limits WinMerge windows to a single instance.
      For example, if WinMerge is already running, a new compare opens in the
      same instance. Without this parameter, multiple windows are allowed:
      depending on other settings, a new compare might open in the existing
      window or in a new window.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>MRU list</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option>/ul</option> prevents WinMerge from adding the left path to
      the Most Recently Used (MRU) list. External applications should not add
      paths to the MRU list in the Select Files or Folders dialog.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option>/ur</option> prevents WinMerge from adding the right path to
      the Most Recently Used (MRU) list. External applications should not add
      paths to the MRU list in the Select Files or Folders dialog.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option>/u</option> prevents WinMerge from adding either path (left
      or right) to the Most Recently Used (MRU) list. External applications
      should not add paths to the MRU list in the Select Files or Folders
      dialog.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>protecting files</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option>/wl</option> opens the left side as read-only. Use this when
      you don't want to change left side items in the compare.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option>/wr</option> opens the right side as read-only. Use this
      when you don't want to change right side items in the compare.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>WinMerge window</primary>

        <secondary>opening minimized or maximized</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option>/minimize</option> starts WinMerge as a minimized window.
      This option can be useful during lengthy compares.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option>/maximize</option> starts WinMerge as a maximized
      window.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option>/dl</option> specifies a description in the left side title
      bar, overriding the default folder or filename text. For example:
      <userinput>/dl "Version 1.0</userinput>" or <userinput>/dl
      WorkingCopy</userinput>. Use quotation marks around descriptions that
      contain spaces.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option>/dr</option> specifies a description in the right side title
      bar, just like <option>/dl</option>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option><replaceable>leftpath</replaceable></option> specifies the
      folder, file, or project file to open on the left side.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><option><replaceable>rightpath</replaceable></option> specifies the
      folder, file, or project file to open on the right side.</para>

      <para>WinMerge cannot compare files to folders, so both path parameters
      (<option><replaceable>leftpath</replaceable></option> and
      <option><replaceable>rightpath</replaceable></option>) must point to the
      same target type (either folders or files). If WinMerge cannot find either
      of the specified paths, it opens the Select Files or Folders dialog, where
      you can browse for the correct paths.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>In file comparisons, you can specify a folder name in one of the
        path parameters, as long as the folder contains a file with the same
        name as the one specified in the other, file path.</para>

        <para>For example, consider this command:</para>

        <para><userinput>WinMergeU <filename>C:\Folder\File.txt</filename>
        <filename class="directory">C:\Folder2</filename> </userinput></para>

        <para>If <filename class="directory">C:\Folder2</filename> contains a
        file named <filename>File.txt</filename>: WinMerge implicitly resolves
        the second path as a file specification, and compares the two files. Of
        course, the command is invalid if <filename
        class="directory">C:\Folder2</filename> does <emphasis>not</emphasis>
        contain a file named <filename>File.txt</filename>.</para>
      </tip>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>merging differences</primary>

        <secondary>result file</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option><replaceable>outputpath</replaceable></option> Specifies an
      optional output folder where you want merged result files to be
      saved.</para>

      <para>The third, output path is rarely needed when you start WinMerge from
      the command line. It is meant to be used with version control tools, where
      you might need to specify a third path for the
      <wordasword>result</wordasword> file. If you specify a third path,
      WinMerge still shows only two files in the File Compare window. However,
      if you save either of these files, it is written to the third path,
      leaving the two source files intact.</para>

      <para>Version control systems typically refer to the source and result
      files using terms like <glossterm>theirs</glossterm>,
      <glossterm>mine</glossterm>, and either <glossterm>merged</glossterm> or
      <glossterm>resolved</glossterm>. If you specify a third path on the
      WinMerge command line, and are working with a version control system, you
      should list the files in that order.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>conflict files</primary>

        <secondary>specifying on command line</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para><option><replaceable>conflictfile</replaceable></option> Specifies a
      conflict file, typically generated by a Version control system. The
      conflict file opens in the File Compare window, where you can merge and
      resolve conflicts, as described in <xref
      linkend="ResolveConflictFiles" />. Note that no other paths can be used
      with a conflict file.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</article>