<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="Configuration">
  <title>Options and configuration<indexterm>
      <primary>options</primary>
    </indexterm></title>

  <para>The Options dialog enables you to customize many WinMerge features. To
  set WinMerge options:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Click <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Options</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> in the menu or the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="16" fileref="screenshots/options_btn.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>WinMerge Options button</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> <guibutton>Options</guibutton> button in the
      toolbar.</para>

      <para>The Options dialog contains a number of pages, each containing a
      group of related options. You can open any page by clicking its title in
      the <guilabel>Categories</guilabel> list, on the left side of the
      dialog.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Configure the options you want to change using one or both of these
      methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Directly in the options pages.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Importing an options <filename>.ini</filename> file that you
          exported previously (see <xref linkend="Configuration_importexport" />
          for details).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>When you have set all your options, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>
      to save them and dismiss the dialog.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>This topic describes the options in detail. There is a section for each
  page in the Options dialog.</para>

  <section id="Configuration_importexport">
    <title>Importing and Exporting options<indexterm>
        <primary>importing options files</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>exporting options files</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>If you change options frequently for different compare or merge
    scenarios, or if you want to share your settings with other WinMerge users,
    consider saving your settings by exporting them to an options file. Then,
    whenever you want to use those settings, you can simply import the options
    file instead of setting options manually.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>To export options</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>When you have set your options the way you want them, click
          <guibutton>Export</guibutton>. In the Select file for export dialog,
          specify a path and name for your options file (the type
          <filename>ini</filename> is automatically appended), and click
          <guibutton>Save</guibutton>.</para>

          <para>In the generated text <filename>ini</filename> file, each line
          contains a name-value pair that defines a single option.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>To import options</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>When you want to reuse your saved options, click
          <guibutton>Import</guibutton>. In the Select file for import dialog,
          navigate to the saved <filename>ini</filename> file and click
          <guibutton>Open</guibutton>.</para>

          <para>The values in your imported options file replace all existing
          settings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_general">
    <title>General options</title>

    <para>The General page has these options:</para>

    <section>
      <title>Automatically scroll to first difference<indexterm>
          <primary>autoscrolling to first difference</primary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): Compare window opens to the
          top of the folder or file, with no difference selected.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: When it first opens, the Compare
          window selects the first difference, scrolling to the location if
          necessary.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>For a folder compare, selects the first different file or
              folders.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>For a file compare, selects the first difference block in
              the files.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Disable splash screen<indexterm>
          <primary>splash screen, disabling</primary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): A splash screen is
          displayed when you start WinMerge. You can dismiss the screen at any
          time by clicking it; otherwise it is automatically dismissed after a
          few seconds.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: Completely omits the splash screen
          when you start WinMerge. Note that this does not make startup
          faster.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Close Windows with <keycap>ESC</keycap><indexterm>
          <primary>closing windows using Esc key</primary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option> (default): Lets you use the
          <keycap>ESC</keycap> key to close WinMerge windows. Pressing
          <keycap>ESC</keycap> once closes one window, so with one File Compare
          window open, it takes three key presses to close WinMerge: first the
          File Compare window, then the Folder Compare window, and finally the
          WinMerge window.</para>

          <para>Note that in the WinMerge command line, the
          <parameter>-e</parameter> parameter enables you to close WinMerge by
          pressing <keycap>ESC</keycap> just once.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option>: Pressing <keycap>ESC</keycap> does
          not close any WinMerge windows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Automatically verify paths in Open-dialog</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option> (default): The Select Files or Folders
          dialog checks both paths as you enter them. The
          <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button remains disabled until both paths are
          validated. Note that this checking can cause some delay.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option>: The <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button
          in the Select Files or Folders dialog is always enabled, and attempts
          to open any paths you specify. Since there is no delay during
          validation, this can speed up the selection of paths. However, if the
          path cannot be opened, an error dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Allow only one instance to run<indexterm>
          <primary>WinMerge window</primary>

          <secondary>opening multiple</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): You can run multiple
          WinMerge instances. For example, if WinMerge is currently running and
          you click the WinMerge desktop shortcut, a new WinMerge window is
          opened.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: Limits the WinMerge program to one
          instance:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If WinMerge is currently running and you try to start a new
              instance, no new application window is opened: the current
              WinMerge window is used instead.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If you start a new instance with paths (for example on the
              command line), a new Compare window is opened in the existing
              WinMerge window.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Also see the related options under <xref
      linkend="Configuration_multicompwin" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ask when closing multiple windows</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): If you exit WinMerge while
          multiple Compare windows are open, WinMerge prompts you to confirm
          whether to close all the windows.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: If you click
          <guibutton>Exit</guibutton> and there are no pending file changes,
          WinMerge closes immediately.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Preserve file time in file compare<indexterm>
          <primary>timestamps</primary>

          <secondary>preserving</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): If you save changes to a
          file in WinMerge, the timestamp of the file is updated.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: If you save changes to a file in
          WinMerge, the timestamp of the file is not changed in your file
          system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Open-dialog Auto-Completion</title>

      <para>Choose one of these options:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Disabled</guilabel> (default): No autocompletion is
          performed when you enter paths in the Select Files or Folders
          dialog.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>From file system</guilabel>: Checks paths as you type.
          It attempts to locate paths in the file system that match the letters
          you type, and if a matching path is found, completes the path.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>From MRU list</guilabel>: Checks paths only from the
          most recently used (MRU) list. This is handy when you have a limited
          set of paths to compare.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="Configuration_multicompwin">
      <title>Enable multiple compare windows for<indexterm>
          <primary>Compare windows</primary>

          <secondary>opening multiple</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Controls whether WinMerge allows you to open single or multiple
      Compare windows. Specify the <guilabel>Folder compare</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>File compare</guilabel> options independently:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): You can only open one
          Folder compare or File compare window at a time.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: You can open multiple Folder or File
          compare windows simultaneously.<note>
              <para>File Compare windows are children of Folder Compare windows.
              Therefore, you can open one File Compare window for every Folder
              Compare window, even if the <guilabel>File compare</guilabel>
              option is disabled.</para>
            </note></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reset</title>

      <para>WinMerge allows you to suppress some common message boxes. For
      example, when two identical files are opened, the message box titled,
      <guilabel>The files are identical</guilabel>, is normally opened. If you
      don't want this box to display any more, you can enable (check) the option
      in that message box to not show the message again.</para>

      <para>Later, you might decide that you want to see those messages again.
      If so, click the <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> button to make the message
      boxes display again.</para>

      <note>
        <para>We recommend that you not suppress messages when updating WinMerge
        to a newer version. The installer enables their display automatically,
        but if you don't use the installer, then remember to enable message
        display by using the <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> button.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_compare">
    <title>Compare options</title>

    <para>The options in this page enable you to change some of the ways that
    WinMerge detects differences, such as comparing only file size, or ignoring
    some types of differences, like case.</para>

    <important>
      <para>Customizing difference detection can be useful during comparisons,
      when you might not be interested in some differences. However, these
      options also affect merging. For example, if you ignore whitespace
      changes, then indentation changes in source code files are not preserved
      when you merge.</para>

      <para>For this reason, before you merge any differences, we strongly
      recommend resetting the options on this page to their default settings,
      especially the ignore options. To reset all the options on this page,
      click the <guibutton>Defaults</guibutton> button.</para>
    </important>

    <section>
      <title>About ignore options<indexterm>
          <primary>ignoring differences</primary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>A number of options in the Compare page (described later in this
      section) enable you to ignore certain differences. Ignored differences are
      treated in special ways in WinMerge:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>They are marked with the Ignored Difference color.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ignored differences cannot be merged</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ignored differences are not included in difference counts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Files containing only ignored differences are marked as
          identical in a folder comparison</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Whitespace<indexterm>
          <primary>whitespace</primary>

          <secondary>detecting and ignoring differences</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Whitespace, the space between words and lines, is represented in
      text files by special, nonprinting characters like spaces, tabs, and
      linefeeds. The significance of whitespace varies a lot: spaces between
      words are usually important; in some text documents, indents and linefeeds
      are critical to meaning and readability; in structured code, linefeeds and
      tabs might be significant.</para>

      <para>These whitespace options are available:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Compare</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Default: All whitespace is compared. If you are not sure which
            option your document requires, this is the safest choice. In the
            example below, all lines are detected as different.</para>

            <example>
              <title>Ignore whitespace change</title>

              <para>One space between words:<screen format="linespecific">Two Words</screen></para>

              <para>Two spaces between words:<screen format="linespecific">Two  Words</screen></para>

              <para>Tab between words:<screen format="linespecific">Two	Words</screen></para>

              <para>No spaces between words:<screen format="linespecific">TwoWords</screen></para>
            </example>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Ignore change</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Compares differences in whitespace. In the preceding example,
            the first three lines have different whitespace, but are detected as
            identical: tabs and multiple are treated as if they are single
            space. The last line has no whitespace, so the difference is
            <emphasis>not</emphasis> ignored (in effect, the words in the last
            two lines are different):</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Ignore all</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Ignores all whitespace characters, except linefeeds (so lines
            are detected, and preserved in a merge). All lines in the preceding
            example are detected as identical.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ignore blank lines<indexterm>
          <primary>blank lines</primary>

          <secondary>detecting and ignoring differences</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): Empty lines in the source
          files are detected and represented in the File Compare window as blank
          lines with the Deleted Difference colors.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: Empty lines in the source files are
          ignored. They are represented in the File Compare window as blank
          lines with the Ignored Difference colors. However the difference
          cannot be merged.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ignore case<indexterm>
          <primary>case (letter), detecting and ignoring differences</primary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): Comparisons are
          case-sensitive. For example, <literal>LowerCase</literal>,
          <literal>LOWERCASE</literal>, and <literal>lowercase</literal> are all
          different.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: Differences between lowercase and
          uppercase letters are ignored.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ignore carriage return differences (Windows/Unix/Mac)<indexterm>
          <primary>EOL</primary>

          <secondary>detecting and ignoring differences</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): WinMerge detects end of
          line (EOL) style differences. For example, if you compare two lines
          that have the same contents but different line endings, the lines are
          considered to be different. When this happens, WinMerge displays a
          dialog prompting you to confirm whether to detect or ignore the
          difference.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: EOL differences are ignored.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Enable moved block detection<indexterm>
          <primary>moved differences</primary>

          <secondary>enabling and disabling detection</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): WinMerge does not detect
          when differences are due to moved lines.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: WinMerge tries to detect lines that
          are moved (in different locations in each file). Moved blocks are
          indicated by the <guilabel>Moved</guilabel> and <guilabel>Selected
          Moved</guilabel> difference colors. If the Location bar is displayed,
          corresponding difference locations in the left and right location bars
          are connected with a line. Showing moved blocks can make it easier to
          visualize changes in files, if there are not too many.</para>

          <para>For an example, see the Location pane description in <xref
          linkend="CompareFiles" />.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Ignore time differences less than 3 seconds<indexterm>
          <primary>timestamps</primary>

          <secondary>detecting and ignoring differences</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): Files with different
          timestamps are detected as different.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: Sometimes (for example, when you use
          network shares) small differences in timestamps are not significant.
          To get more meaningful results in such situations, this option enables
          you to ignore time differences smaller than three seconds.</para>

          <para>This option works only with the <guimenuitem>Modified
          Date</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Modified Date and
          Size</guimenuitem> compare methods (described in <xref
          linkend="Configuration_compmethod" />). It has no effect with other
          methods.</para>

          <warning>
            <para>This option should be enabled only when the time difference is
            detected. Otherwise, it can cause incorrect compare results.</para>
          </warning>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="Configuration_compmethod">
      <title>File Compare method<indexterm>
          <primary>comparing files</primary>

          <secondary>detection options</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>This option lets you determine how complete your file comparisons
      are. Choose one of these five choices:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Full Contents</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Default: Full comparison of files by content, with all the
            bells and whistles. This method invokes plugins and uses the
            diffutils engine for fully accurate differencing and moved block
            detection. This is the most complete and recommended method.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Quick Contents</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Slimmed-down comparison of files by content. This method uses
            streamlined file comparison code which skips plugins and moved block
            detection. This method is faster than <guilabel>Full
            Contents</guilabel>, because it does not load the files.</para>

            <para>Its drawback is that line filters are not applied when
            comparing. For example, this method sees file as different even if
            line filters are set to ignore all differences in the files.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Modified Date<indexterm>
              <primary>timestamps</primary>

              <secondary>comparing</secondary>
            </indexterm></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Compares only the modification dates on the files, so it is
            far faster than either of the contents methods. But obviously, it is
            only as accurate as the modification dates.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Modified Date and Size</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Similar to <guilabel>Modified Date</guilabel>, but also checks
            file sizes when dates are identical.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Size<indexterm>
              <primary>file sizes</primary>

              <secondary>comparing</secondary>
            </indexterm></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Compares only file sizes, so it is fast but not as accurate as
            the contents methods.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Stop after first difference<indexterm>
          <primary>comparing files</primary>

          <secondary>stopping after first difference</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>comparing folders</primary>

          <secondary>stopping after first difference</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>This option is enabled only when the <guilabel>Quick
      Contents</guilabel> compare method is selected.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): WinMerge examines all
          differences in the files.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: This option optimizes comparisons by
          examining files only until the first difference is found, instead
          always scanning the entire files.</para>

          <para>The drawback is that WinMerge may be unable to identify binary
          files as binary. This is likely to happen if the first difference is
          near the beginning of the file. If you know what kind of files you are
          comparing (for example, which are binary files), this option can be a
          good way to speed up comparisons. However, don't enable this option if
          you are not sure what kind of files you are comparing.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Filter Comments<indexterm>
          <primary>filtering</primary>

          <secondary>comments</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <!--Just guessing what this does - ask a developer.-->

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): WinMerge compares comments
          in code, along with other content.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: This option optimizes comparisons by
          detecting comments in certain programming language file types (such as
          C++ and Java), and ignoring them.</para>

          <para>The recognized file types and their comment markers are defined
          in the file, <filename>IgnoreSectionMarkers.ini</filename>, at the top
          of the WinMerge installation directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_editor">
    <title>Editor options<indexterm>
        <primary>editing</primary>

        <secondary>options for File Compare window</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <section id="Configuration_syntaxhighlight">
      <title>Syntax highlighting<indexterm>
          <primary>syntax highlighting</primary>

          <secondary>enabling and disabling</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option> (default): WinMerge can syntax
          highlight many programming language and web formats. To see the
          formats that are supported by default, click <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>View</guimenu>

              <guimenuitem>Syntax Highlight</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option>: Syntax highlighting consumes some
          processing power, so if WinMerge screen updating seems to be slow,
          turning off this option might help.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Automatic rescan<indexterm>
          <primary>rescanning files</primary>

          <secondary>enabling and disabling autoscan</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): WinMerge rescans
          automatically when you merge a difference, or if you manually rescan
          (for example, click the <guibutton>Rescan</guibutton> button).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: Forces WinMerge to rescan after every
          edit event (a change to files, like typing).</para>

          <note>
            <para>To avoid slowing down your editing, WinMerge delays automatic
            rescanning a little: it waits one second after each edit event.
            Because each new edit event resets the timer, no rescans occur until
            you pause or stop editing.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Preserve original EOL chars<indexterm>
          <primary>EOL</primary>

          <secondary>preserving</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>end of line</primary>

          <see>EOL</see>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): Assumes that files are
          meant to be Windows files. If a file does not use the standard Windows
          line ending, WinMerge considers this to be an error. It silently
          changes the line endings to the Windows style instead of detecting
          them as differences. Thus, the File Compare window status bar shows
          the EOL style as <guilabel>Win</guilabel>.</para>

          <para>For most situations, you should leave this option disabled: this
          default behavior works even when comparing two files that have
          different line ending styles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: Prevents WinMerge from automatically
          changing line endings, so that it detects different EOL styles for
          every line. This might be useful for handling files from systems with
          different EOL styles (for example, Windows and Unix).</para>

          <important>
            <para>This is an advanced option for users who are familiar with EOL
            bytes and who want to compare files with different EOL styles inside
            <emphasis>one</emphasis> file. We recommend that you not enable this
            option unless you need this advanced functionality. Remember, this
            option is not required to compare two files with different EOL
            styles.</para>
          </important>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tab options<indexterm>
          <primary>tabs</primary>

          <secondary>editing options</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tab size</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Width of a tab space. Specify a value
            <replaceable>n</replaceable> : the resulting width is equivalent to
            that of <replaceable>n</replaceable> characters. Default: 4. The
            maximum value is 64.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tab insert options</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Determines what kind of character is used when you insert a
            tab in text. Only one of these options can be enabled:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Insert Tabs</guilabel> (default): Uses a single
                tab character.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><guilabel>Insert Spaces</guilabel>: Uses one or more
                spaces (determined by the <option>Tab size</option>) instead of
                a tab character. For example, with the default tab size, four
                spaces are inserted.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>View line differences<indexterm>
          <primary>line differences</primary>

          <secondary>viewing options</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>WinMerge can highlight not only different lines, but also
      differences within lines. You can enable and disable line difference
      coloring using either the <guilabel>View Line Differences</guilabel>
      option in this page, or by clicking <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>View</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>View Line Differences</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>. For example, when the menu item is checked, the option in
      this page is also checked, and changing either setting automatically
      changes the other.</para>

      <para>However, <guilabel>View Line Differences</guilabel> and the options
      under it give you control over exactly what kinds of differences are
      detected within lines:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option> (default): WinMerge highlights
          differences within lines (also enables the <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>View</guimenu>

              <guimenuitem>View Line Differences</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> menu item).</para>

          <para>When this option is enabled, you can choose one of these
          suboptions. The best choice usually depends on the file types you are
          comparing:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Character level</guilabel>: Detects individual
              characters that are different. This option can be useful for file
              formats that do not have clear word breaks, or if you are looking
              for single-character differences. For example, this level makes it
              easy to spot a single changed character in the middle of a
              word.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Word-level</guilabel> (default): Detects words
              that are different. Possible advantage: making it easy to copy and
              paste words.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Break at whitespace</guilabel> (default):
                  Words are assumed to be separated by whitespace characters.
                  This usually works for typical text files.</para>

                  <para>For example, these two lines contain punctuation but no
                  whitespace. So, with the <guilabel>Break at
                  whitespace</guilabel> option, WinMerge detects no word breaks.
                  Instead, it highlights the text as a single word-level line
                  difference.</para>

                  <para><screen>10,20,30,40,50</screen></para>

                  <para><screen>10,25,30,45,50</screen></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Break at whitespace or punctuation</guilabel>:
                  Considers both whitespace and punctuation characters to be
                  word breaks. This is useful for handling lists that are
                  separated with punctuation (like comma-separated lists). In
                  the preceding example, WinMerge highlights only 20 and 40 in
                  the first line, and 25 and 45 in the second line.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option>: WinMerge does not highlight
          differences within lines, and all settings for the level and
          whitespace options are ignored (also disables the <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>View</guimenu>

              <guimenuitem>View Line Differences</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> menu item).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_colors">
    <title>Colors options<indexterm>
        <primary>difference colors</primary>

        <secondary>options</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Use this page if you want to change any of the difference colors used
    in the File Compare window. You can set the background, deleted, and text
    color.</para>

    <para>To change a color, click in its box to open a standard Color chooser
    dialog. Choose one of the predefined colors or define your own custom color,
    then click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to load the new color in the
    box.</para>

    <para>At any time, you can click <guibutton>Defaults</guibutton> to reload
    the installed color scheme.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_textcolors">
    <title>Text Colors options<indexterm>
        <primary>text colors</primary>

        <secondary>options</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>Use this page to change the colors used for text. First, check the
    option, <guilabel>Use customized text colors</guilabel>. This activates the
    text options. There is an option for three kinds of text: whitespace,
    regular text, and selected text. For each kind of text , you can choose a
    color for the background and the text.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_syntaxcolors">
    <title>Syntax Colors options<indexterm>
        <primary>syntax highlighting</primary>

        <secondary>color options</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>By default, the WinMerge File Compare window marks the syntax of
    certain kinds of source code, as described in <xref
    linkend="Configuration_syntaxhighlight" />. This page lists the syntax
    elements that are recognized, and enables you to change their text color and
    weight.</para>

    <para>At any time, you can click <guibutton>Defaults</guibutton> to reload
    the installed color scheme.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_archive">
    <title>Archive Support<indexterm>
        <primary>archiving files</primary>

        <secondary>configuring support after installation</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>This page contains options for configuring Winzip archive support
    using 7-Zip.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Download 7-zip Plugin<indexterm>
          <primary>7-Zip archive support</primary>

          <secondary>options</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>If WinZip is already installed on your system, WinMerge
      automatically detects it, and you don't need to configure anything here.
      Otherwise, you can click this link to open the WinMerge downloads page in
      your Web browser. There, you can download the 7-Zip Plugin installer (and
      other WinMerge files). To install the plugin, see <xref
      linkend="Installing_archive_support" />. Remember to close WinMerge before
      running the 7-Zip installer.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Enable archive file support</title>

      <para>This option controls how WinMerge handles archive files (based on
      7-Zip integration).</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option> (default): WinMerge recognizes 7-Zip
          archives.</para>

          <para>WinMerge can access 7-Zip from two installation sources. If you
          specified one of these methods earlier (for example, during the
          WinMerge installation), you can change it here:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Use stand-alone 7-Zip if available</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Use local 7-Zip from WinMerge folder</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option>: Turns off 7-Zip archive
          integration.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Detect archive type from file signature</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): WinMerge recognizes only
          archives whose file extension is known on your system (for example, in
          the registry or through a file association).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: WinMerge can recognize archive files
          even if their file extension is not known. To recognize an archive,
          WinMerge searches the beginning of the file for the archive signature
          bytes.<tip>
              <para>You can use this option to enable WinMerge to recognize Open
              Office files.</para>
            </tip></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_system">
    <title>System options</title>

    <section>
      <title>Send deleted files to Recycle Bin<indexterm>
          <primary>deleting files</primary>

          <secondary>options</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option> (default): Files and folders that you
          deletein a Folder Compare window are moved to the Recycle Bin, if it
          is available.</para>

          <important>
            <para>Remember: if the Recycle Bin on your system has been
            deactivated, this option does not work, and deleted files are
            lost!</para>
          </important>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option>: Files and folders deleted in a
          directory compare actually deleted.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Add to explorer context menu<indexterm>
          <primary>shell integration</primary>

          <secondary>enabling and disabling</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option> (default): Adds one or more WinMerge
          shortcuts to the Windows Explorer context menu. After right-clicking
          one or more files or folders, choose a WinMerge shortcut to open the
          items in a WinMerge compare window.</para>

          <para>Two additional options are available if you use this
          integration. Neither option is enabled by default, but you can enable
          one or both:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Enable advanced menu</term>

              <listitem>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): The
                    <guimenuitem>WinMerge</guimenuitem> shortcut is included in
                    the Windows Explorer context menu when you right-click one
                    or more files or folders. If you select a single item, the
                    Select Files or Folders dialog opens. If you select two
                    items, they are opened directly in a Compare window.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><option>Enabled</option>: Replaces the
                    <guimenuitem>WinMerge</guimenuitem> shortcut in the Explorer
                    context menu with <guimenuitem>Compare</guimenuitem>
                    shortcuts, described in <xref
                    linkend="OpenPaths_shell-integ" />. The
                    <guimenuitem>Compare</guimenuitem> shortcuts enable you to
                    add a selected path to memory, then choose the second
                    separately (for example, in a different Explorer
                    view).</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Include subfolders by default</term>

              <listitem>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): When you use the
                    <guimenuitem>WinMerge</guimenuitem> or
                    <guimenuitem>Compare</guimenuitem> shortcut, only the top
                    level of files is selected: the compare operation is
                    non-recursive.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><option>Enabled</option>: The selection includes
                    subfolders, making the compare operation recursive.</para>

                    <para>Another way to include subfolders is to press
                    <keycap>Control</keycap> while selecting the
                    <guimenuitem>WinMerge</guimenuitem> or
                    <guimenuitem>Compare</guimenuitem> shortcut in the Windows
                    Explorer context menu.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option>: The
          <guimenuitem>WinMerge</guimenuitem> shortcut is unavailable in Windows
          Explorer.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>External editor<indexterm>
          <primary>external editor</primary>

          <secondary>configuring</secondary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>The WinMerge File Compare window provides common editing functions.
      If you prefer using your favorite, full-featured editor, you can configure
      WinMerge to open an external editor from the Folder Compare context
      menu.</para>

      <para>By default, Notepad is configured as the default external editor,
      because it is found on all Windows systems. To configure a different
      external editor, enter the full path to its executable file.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>Along with the path, you can include any command line parameters
        supported by the external tool, in this format:
        <command><replaceable>path to executable</replaceable></command>
        <option>-option1</option> <option>-option2</option>
        <option><replaceable>...</replaceable></option></para>
      </tip>

      <para>To use the configured external editor, right-click a file in the
      Folder Compare window and choose <menuchoice>
          <guimenuitem>Open Left</guimenuitem>

          <guimenuitem>with External Editor</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> or <menuchoice>
          <guimenuitem>Open Right</guimenuitem>

          <guimenuitem>with External Editor</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Filter Folder<indexterm>
          <primary>filtering, folder used</primary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Use this field to specify your own private folder for file filters.
      By default this folder is your user profile directory (for example,
      <filename>My Documents</filename> on Windows XP, or
      <filename>Documents</filename> on Windows Vista). When you create a file
      filter, it is automatically added to this folder.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Temporary files folder<indexterm>
          <primary>temporary files, folder used</primary>
        </indexterm></title>

      <para>Specify the folder where WinMerge stores temporary files. Either one
      of these options is available:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>System's temp folder (default): For example, this might be
          <filename>C:\Windows\Temp</filename> on your system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom folder: Click <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> and select a
          different folder where you have write access.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_backup">
    <title>Backup Files<indexterm>
        <primary>backup files, options</primary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>This page allows you to control how WinMerge creates backup
    files.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Create backup files in</title>

      <para>Specify when WinMerge should create backup files. You can enable or
      disable each of these options independently:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Folder compare</guilabel> (disabled by default):
          Backup files are create whenever files are overwritten
          (copied).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>File compare</guilabel> (enabled by default): Backup
          files are created whenever files are saved.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Create backup files into</title>

      <para>Specify where backup files are created. Only one of these options
      can be enabled:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Original file's folder</guilabel> (enabled by
          default): Backup files are created in the same folder as the source
          file. This is usually a good choice. The down side is that cleaning up
          backup files in big folders can take a lot of work.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Global backup folder</guilabel> (disabled by default):
          All backup files are created in one global folder. This makes them
          easy to clean up. But, if there are multiple source files with same
          file name, then the most recent backup file overwrites the previous
          one of the same name.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Backup filename</title>

      <para>When WinMerge creates a backup file, it appends an extension to the
      source file name. You can choose either or both of these extension
      schemes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Append .bak -extension</guilabel> (enabled by
          default): For example, the <filename>file.txt</filename> is backed up
          to <filename>file.txt.bak</filename>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>File compare</guilabel> (enabled by default):
          Timestamps are almost always unique, so this option usually avoids
          duplicating backup file names when the source files have the same
          names.</para>

          <para>Also, storing a copy of a file each time you save it provides a
          way to track changes to the file. However, you should consider that
          this option can create a lot of files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_vcs">
    <title>Version Control options<indexterm>
        <primary>version control systems</primary>

        <secondary>integration configuration</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <!--What does version control integration do for me? How do the Option page settings work with installed 
VCS integration? My installation had an option to integrate with TortoiseSVN.-->

    <para>Use this page to configure or disable the WinMerge integration with a
    supported versioning system.</para>

    <para>Choose one of these options:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>None</guilabel> (default)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Visual SourceSafe (less than 5.0)</guilabel></para>

        <para>Also enter the path to <filename>SS.EXE</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Visual SourceSafe (5.0 and above)</guilabel></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Rational ClearCase</guilabel></para>

        <para>Also enter the path to <filename>cleartool.exe</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="Configuration_codepage">
    <title>Codepage options<indexterm>
        <primary>codepage</primary>

        <secondary>options</secondary>
      </indexterm></title>

    <para>This page allow you to specify the codepage that WinMerge uses for
    ANSI files, and whether the codepage of certain file formats should be
    detected from the contents of the files.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Default codepage for ANSI files</title>

      <para>Choose one of these radio buttons to set the default codepage that
      WinMerge uses when handling ANSI files:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>System codepage</guilabel> (default):The codepage used
          by your Windows system. This default is usually the best choice.
          However if you know that you are comparing files that do not use the
          system codepage, consider one of the other options.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>According to WinMerge User Interface</guilabel>: The
          encoding used by your installation of WinMerge.<!--This is just a guess - don't find any info on this option.--></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Custom codepage</guilabel>: Enter the codepage number
          explicitly. For example, <userinput>UTF-8</userinput> or
          <userinput>ISO-8851-1</userinput>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Detect codepage info for these files: .html .rc .xml</title>

      <important>
        <para>Uncheck this option in <filename>WinMerge.exe</filename>.
        Characters conversions can result in lossy conversions and the risk is
        very high. <filename>WinMerge.exe</filename> can display files only with
        your current codepage.<!--What option? The one in the Options page? If it should always be unchecked, 
why is the option there? Also, should we mention WinMergeU.exe when we mention WinMerge.exe,
or is this understood?--></para>
      </important>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>Disabled</option> (default): WinMerge does not read
          codepage information from the source files. It uses the default
          codepage setting instead.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><option>Enabled</option>: WinMerge detects the codepage for
          these extensions : <filename class="extension">html</filename>,
          <filename class="extension">rc</filename> (resource files for VC++)
          and <filename class="extension">xml</filename>. The detected codepage
          overrides the setting for the default codepage option.</para>

          <para>This option is of interest when your documents use a codepage
          that is different from the codepage of your Windows
          configuration.</para>

          <para>For example, you might merge two Slovak or two Japanese files in
          an English environment. With this option enabled (and with the
          required fonts), your Slovak, or Japanese, the files are displayed
          using Slovak, or Japanese, characters.</para>

          <para>WinMerge also detects a codepage difference between the
          left/right files. To avoid lossy conversions when you merge, copy, or
          paste, we suggest that you ignore the codepage information.</para>

          <caution>
            <para>When you copy or paste text to an external application, the
            external application must use the same codepage as WinMerge does.
            Refer to the documentation for your external editor. For copying to
            WinMerge, Internet Explorer offers codepage selection. If your
            external editor does not support custom codepages, disable this
            option.</para>
          </caution>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
