<sect1>
  <title>Options &amp; configuration</title>
  <para>Options dialog can be opened from View-menu or from toolbar button. Changes made are saved when dialog is closed using OK-button (or pressing Enter-key).</para>
  <sect2>
    <title>General options</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>Backup original file</title>
      <para>When this option is enabled backup copy of file is created every time before saving the file. Filename for backup file is generated by replacing filename extension with "BAK".</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Automatically scroll to first difference</title>
      <para>When this option is enabled:<simplelist>
          <member>after directory compare selection is moved to first different files or directories</member>
          <member>after opening files for compare first difference in files is scrolled visible and selecteds</member>
        </simplelist></para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Disable splash screen</title>
      <para>User can disable splash screen appearing when WinMerge is started. It does not make WinMerge start faster (splash screen can be missed by clicking it with mouse) but it saves one click.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Close compare statepane automatically</title>
      <para>User can allow WinMerge to close compare statepane automatically after directory compare is ready. After compare statuspane is closed it can be reopened from View-menu (Compare Statepane).</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Close Windows with ESC</title>
      <para>If this option is enabled, WinMerge closes document windows and application with ESC key. One window is closed with one keypress, so if user has file compare window open one needs three keypresses to close WinMerge: file compare window, directory compare window and then the application.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Automatically verify paths in Open-dialog</title>
      <para>When enabled: Open-dialog checks both paths given for validity and doesn't enable "OK" button until both paths are valid. Unfortunately this checking needs little delay and some users find this delay annoying.</para>
      <para>When disabled: Open-dialog enabled "OK" button by default and lets user to try to open all paths. However error message is shown if path is not valid. This is faster to use, there is no any delay in enabling "OK". But user must look at error-dialogs.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Compare options</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>Whitespace</title>
      <para>Compare Whitespace, Ignore whitespace change and Ignore all whitespace are three different levels for comparing/ignoring whitespace characters.</para>
      <important>
        <para>Ignoring whitespaces affects merging! If user ignores whitespace changes, then e.g. indentation changes in source code files are ignored. That means file's indentation gets messed up when merging. It is strongly recommended to set whitespace option to "Compare All" before merging files.</para>
      </important>
      <para>"Ignore whitespace change" ignores changes in whitespace chars. First three lines in example below illustrate this, those three lines are detected as identical if this option is set. However change between zero and more whitespace characters is NOT ignored. So fourth line is different from first two lines<example>
          <title>Ignore whitespace change</title>
          <para>One space between words:<screen format="linespecific">Two Words</screen></para>
          <para>Two spaces between words:<screen format="linespecific">Two  Words</screen></para>
          <para>Tab between words:<screen format="linespecific">Two	Words</screen></para>
          <para>No spaces between words:<screen format="linespecific">TwoWords</screen></para>
        </example></para>
      <para>"Ignore all whitespace" ignores all whitespace characters. All lines in example below are detected as identical.<example>
          <title>Ignore all whitespace</title>
          <para>One space between words:<screen format="linespecific">Two Words</screen></para>
          <para>Tab between words:<screen format="linespecific">Two	Words</screen></para>
          <para>No spaces between words:<screen format="linespecific">TwoWords</screen></para>
        </example></para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Ignore blank lines</title>
      <para>Ignores differences consisting only of blank lines in files. Blank lines are shown in file view, but difference is not shown as mergeable difference.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Ignore case</title>
      <para>If this option is enabled WinMerge ignores differences between lowercase and uppercase letters. For example "LowerCase" and "LOWERCASE" and "lowercase" are same.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Ignore carriage return differences (DOS/UNIX/MAC)</title>
      <para>If this option is not set WinMerge does not detect EOL style differences as differences. If two lines differ only by EOL characters (e.g. DOS EOL and Unix EOL) WinMerge detects files as identical.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Enable moved block detection</title>
      <para>When this option is enabled WinMerge tries to detect lines that are moved inside file. Moved lines have own difference colors. Also location pane can show moved lines with line between bars. This makes it easier to visualise changes in files. However if there are a lot of moved lines it may get messy looking.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>File compare method</title>
      <para>File compare method has two choises:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Contents - compares files by content of files. This is accurate and recommended compare method.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Modified date - compares files by modified date. This can greatly speedup comparing lot of files. But on the other hand results may not be accurate.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para></para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Editor options</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>Syntax highlighting</title>
      <para>From "Hilighting" -page user can enable/disable syntax highlighting. WinMerge can syntax highlight many programming language source codes, web formats etc. Syntax hilighting consumes some processing power, so if WinMerge screen updating seems to be slow, turning off this option might help.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Apply to unrecognized side</title>
      <para>When this options is enabled WinMerge applies known know file format's syntax highligh to another file even if that file's extension is not known. For example, if you compare files, file.cpp and file.cpp.bak, WinMerge detects file.cpp needs C++ syntax highlight. And then uses same rules for file.cpp.bak too.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Automatic rescan</title>
      <para>Enabling automatic rescanning forces WinMerge to rescan after every change done to files, including typing. That's how WinMerge 1.7.1 behaves. For bigger files this can make editing files very slow. To make file editing faster edit events are 'delayed'.</para>
      <para>Delaying means WinMerge waits one second after last edit event before rescanning. If new edit event happens during that time editing is done and counter reset to one second. So there should be no rescans during normal typing, but only after user stops typing.</para>
      <para>When automatic rescan is disabled, rescan is done only when user selects "rescan" or user merges difference.</para>
      <para>WinMerge 2.2 release delays more edit events than 2.0.x releases, so selecting between automatic and manual rescan is mostly a matter of taste.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Preserve original EOL chars</title>
      <important>
        <para>This is an advanced option for advanced users familiar with EOL bytes. For comparing files with different EOL styles inside ONE file. If comparing that kind of files is not needed, don't set this option.</para>
      </important>
      <para>Setting this option allows handling and comparing files with different EOL styles inside ONE file. Two files with different EOL styles can be compared even without this option set! One example reveals functionality behind this option.</para>
      <screen format="linespecific">This is one example 
text. To show how
smart WinMerge
can be handling 
EOL differences.</screen>
      <para>And same text in bytes:</para>
      <screen format="linespecific">5468 6973 2069 7320 6F6E 6520 6578 616D 706C 6520 0D0A
7465 7874 2E20 546F 2073 686F 7720 686F 7720 0D0A
736D 6172 7420 5769 6E4D 6572 6765 0D
6361 6E20 6265 2068 616E 646C 696E 6720 0D0A
454F 4C20 6469 6666 6572 656E 6365 732E</screen>
      <para>The example presents one simplish text file with five lines of text. All lines, except third, are terminated with DOS style EOL (0D0A). Third line has Unix style EOL (0D).</para>
      <para>If "Preserve original EOL chars" -option is not set WinMerge determines file is meant to be DOS style file and converts third line's last bytes to 0D0A before comparing. Missing EOL char is usually an error in file, so WinMerge is smart and fixes this error instead of reporting it as a difference. That's right, WinMerge changes user's file without telling about it to user. WinMerge also shows files EOL style as "DOS" in filecompare statusbar.</para>
      <para>Advanced user might want to handle files without this automatic fixing, file might be handled in systems with different EOL styles (e.g. Windows and Linux). In that case, user can set this option and see WinMerge showing EOL style for every line.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Tab options</title>
      <para>From General -page user can set size tabulator character in spaces. Maximum value is 64.</para>
      <para>Another selection is if user wants WinMerge to add tab characters or spaces (amount specified by tab size -option) when tab -key is pressed.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>System options</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>Put deleted files to Recycle Bin</title>
      <para>When this options is enabled files and folders deleted in directory compare are put to Recycle Bin. Note that use of Recycle Bin may have disabled from system.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Add to explorer context menu</title>
      <para>This option enables/disables shell integration. When enabled, new menuitem "WinMerge" is added to explorer's context menu. User can select one or two files/folders and then select that menuitem to open files/folders to WinMerge.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Enable advanced menu</title>
      <para>If this option is enabled there are two items shown in explorer's context menu. First item allows user to select path to "memory" and then pick another path and compare those two. This means user does not need to select both paths from same view, but user can select them from different drives etc. Path is forgotten from memory when its compared.</para>
      <para>Second item in menu always opens WinMerge with selected path(s).</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>External editor</title>
      <para>WinMerge has pretty good editor for most basic editing needs. But its not nowhere near comparable to many other editors in functionality. So WinMerge allows user to define ones personally preferred editor to external editor. Files can be opened to external editor from directory compare's context menu.</para>
      <para>Notepad is used as default, because it is found from all Windows machines. Commandline parameters can be given, in format: &lt;path to .exe&gt; -option1 -option2 ...</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
