<sect1 id="Faq">
  <title>Frequently asked questions</title>
  <sect2>
    <title>General questions</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Why is there two executable files, WinMerge.exe and WinMergeU.exe?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>WinMerge.exe is ANSI executable which works in all 32-bit Windows systems. It does not have Unicode support.</para>
              <para>Internally, it stores only ANSI characters (256 possibilities). If you open an Unicode (65536 possible characters) file, the characters must be converted to the ANSI character set. Conversion can be approximative (accents are lost), or impossible (characters appear as "?").</para>
              <para>WinMerge.exe can neither open files when filename is not writeable in the current ANSI set.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>WinMergeU.exe is Unicode enabled executable which works in Windows NT4, Windows 2000 and newer systems.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>That splash screen is annoying, how do I turn it off?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>From menu, select Edit -&gt; Options... -&gt; Disable Splash Screen</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>When wanting to compare directories, I cannot select a directory in Browse?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Are you trying to select a directory by clicking on it in the upper part of the Open File dialog ? The OpenFile dialog will then open it, and you have to push Ok again to get out.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Does WinMerge support merging three files? Sometimes called 3-way merge, where one file is ancestor. This would be useful for version control!</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Unfortunately not. We acknowledge it would be good feature but we don't have plans currently to implement it. It is hard UI and usability problem. Quality of existing 3-way merging tools varies a lot and we don't want to implement it if we are not sure we can do it with quality. This can be somewhat work-arounded using two WinMerge instances.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Do you have plans to support other OSes than Windows?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Not currently. If somebody wants to work with cross-platform support (using wxWidgets for example) we are interested in helping of course.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Questions about binary files</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>WinMerge says "Binary files are different", but I am not comparing binary files?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>If you are using WinMerge.exe (not WinMergeU.exe), then your files may be Unicode files. WinMerge.exe cannot handle Unicode files. Please try comparing files with WinMergeU.exe if you have Windows NT4, Windows 2000 or newer.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>WinMerge cannot compare registry files (*.reg)?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Windows registry files (*.reg) are Unicode files (UTF-16 or UCS-2) -- see previous answer.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>I cannot merge binary files?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>WinMerge can only show if binary files are identical or different.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Questions about editor</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Some characters are cut in half?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Try selecting a different font from menu View -&gt; Select Font...</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>I would like to see the line numbers?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>WinMerge shows current line in editor statusbar. WinMerge cannot show in-editor linenumbers. That is anyhow one feature we might consider for future releases.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>I see question marks instead of letters in files?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>This is what we call a "lossy" conversion.</para>
          <para>For Unicode files (UCS-2, UTF-8), use WinMergeU.exe.</para>
          <para>For ANSI files, this is propably due to code-page problem. If 'Use codepage info' is selected from options, turn that off and see if it helps.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>I cannot select proportional fonts for editor?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Unfortunately WinMerge 2.0 or 2.2 supports only non-proportional fonts.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>WinMerge as external compare or diff-tool</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>I want that WinMerge is closed with single ESC press after I'm done?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Use -e commandline switch.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>How can I avoid temporary paths filling Open-dialog history lists?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Tell program to invoke WinMerge with the /ub option, which tells WinMerge to not add the files to the MRU.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>But program I'm using doesn't allow commandline parameters!</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>Create a batch file where you add one of these lines (but not both):</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <screen>CALL "&lt;winmerge path&gt;\WinMerge" /ub %1 %2</screen>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <screen>start "WinMerge" "&lt;winmerge path&gt;" /ub %1 %2</screen>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>And then call this batch file from program.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Archive support</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>What means messagebox "Merge7z*.dll was not found."?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>WinMerge uses Merge7z*.dll files for archive support using 7-zip. There must be matching version of Merge7z*.dll to 7-zip version installed. For example if 7-zip version 3.11 is installed, there must be Merge7z311.dll present. WinMerge is installed with several versions of that DLL. If there is no such DLL, please check if WinMerge project pages at SourceForge.net have updated DLL or install package available.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>How can I open 'Perry-style' patch files WinMerge developers use when submitting pathes?</para>
        </question>
        <answer>
          <para>'Perry-style' patches are zip-files containing original and changed files in different directories. WinMerge has internal support (surprise?) for handling these files. Just select zip file in guestion to left side and right side and WinMerge opens zip files contents to directory compare comparing original and altered files.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
