<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="Installing">
  <title>Getting and installing WinMerge</title>

  <para>WinMerge can be installed using the installer or by unzipping files from
  an archive. Using the installer is the recommended method.</para>

  <note>
    <para>Currently the WinMerge installer works natively only for 32-bit
    Windows. There is no separate version of WinMerge for 64-bit Windows
    (WinXP/2003/Vista). 64-bit Windows versions can run the installer and
    WinMerge as 32-bit applications. For the shell Integration, the installer
    includes the 64-bit version of the extension.</para>
  </note>

  <section>
    <title>Getting files</title>

    <para>The latest release can be always downloaded from the WinMerge home
    page: <ulink url="http://winmerge.org/">WinMerge.org</ulink>. Note that
    delays can occur in updating home pages for the latest releases, but the
    project status page at <ulink
    url="https://sourceforge.net/projects/winmerge/">SourceForge.net</ulink>
    shows the latest files. There is also a mailing list for release
    announcements. Stable releases are also available in several file download
    sites.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the installer (recommended)</title>

    <note>
      <para>The installer requires Administrator user privileges in Windows
      NT4/2000/XP. If you don't have admin user privileges, you can install
      WinMerge by unzipping from an archive file (see <xref
      linkend="InstallFromArchive" />).</para>
    </note>

    <para>Using the installer is recommended for most users. The installer
    prompts for the location where WinMerge is installed. It then installs the
    files, configures the shell integration, and adds WinMerge to the Start
    menu. To install WinMerge:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Start the installer executable (usually named
        <filename>WinMerge-<replaceable>version</replaceable>-setup.exe</filename>).</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> in the Welcome
        screen.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton> in the License Agreement
        screen.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>In the Select Destination Location page, accept the location
        for WinMerge or, if you choose another location, we recommend that you
        install WinMerge in its own folder. Click
        <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>In the Select Components page, choose one of the preconfigured
        installations in the top control. We recommend the
        <guilabel>Typical</guilabel> configuration for most users. The lower box
        shows all the available components. You can modify a preconfigured
        installation by checking or unchecking components. For example, you
        might choose additional language files. Components are:</simpara>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>WinMerge core files</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>WinMerge executable, Help, and other needed files. Cannot be
              unchecked.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Filters</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>File filter files</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Plugins</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Plugins and scripts</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Languages</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>WinMerge translation files. After installing translation
              file user interface language can be selected from menu <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>View</guimenu>

                  <guimenuitem>Language</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>In the Select Start Menu Folder page, configure WinMerge
        shortcuts.</simpara>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Accept the default setting to create a program shortcut, or
            specify a different folder.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Optionally, check the option, <guilabel>Don't create a Start
            Menu folder</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the Select Additional Tasks page, specify any additional
        tasks:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Enable Explorer context menu integration</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Enables basic WinMerge shell integration (can be enabled
              later in WinMerge options).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Integrate with TortoiseCVS</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sets WinMerge to be the TortoiseCVS diff application.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Integrate with TortoiseSVN</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sets WinMerge to be the TortoiseSVN diff application</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Integrate with ClearCase</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sets WinMerge to be the ClearCase diff and merge
              application</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Create a Desktop shortcut</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Adds the WinMerge shortcut to your Desktop.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Create a Quick Launch shortcut</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Adds the WinMerge shortcut to Quick Launch bar.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>Click <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>In the Ready to Install page, verify your install selections.
        If necessary, click <guibutton>Back</guibutton> to change anything in a
        previous page. When you are sure that you are ready to proceed, click
        <guibutton>Install</guibutton>.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>After the installer has copied files, the final screen appears.
        Using the two check boxes, confirm whether the created WinMerge Start
        menu folder should be opened, and whether the WinMerge application
        should be started.</simpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="InstallFromArchive">Installing from an archive</title>

    <para>WinMerge is pretty much independent of other system components. It is
    not tightly integrated with Windows, and does not use many DLLs.</para>

    <para><filename>WinMerge[U].exe</filename> itself depends on
    <filename>MFC71[U].dll</filename> , <filename>MSVCR71.dll and
    MSVCP71.dll</filename>, in addition to some system DLLs. So if these DLLs
    are already installed on a system, only <filename>WinMerge[U].exe</filename>
    is needed to run WinMerge. The DLL files listed above are also available as
    a downloadable runtime package.</para>

    <note>
      <para>WinMerge 2.6.0 and later versions require a new version of runtime
      libraries. When you update from older WinMerge versions using archive
      files, you need the new runtime files from the runtime package.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Archive files have the correct folder structure. WinMerge should be
    unzipped preserving this folder structure in the destination folder. For
    example, the root folder created under <filename
    class="directory">C:\Program Files\</filename> has the name, <filename
    class="directory">WinMerge-<replaceable>version</replaceable></filename>
    (for example, <filename class="directory">WinMerge-2.6.0</filename>). You
    can rename this folder or copy its files to another folder (preserving the
    folder structure!).</para>

    <para>After the files are unzipped, WinMerge is ready to run! Shell
    integration and archive integration may need additional steps, as described
    in the next section.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Shell integration</title>

    <para>The installer enables shell integration when you choose the
    <guilabel>Enable Explorer context menu integration</guilabel> option in the
    Select Additional Tasks page. If you do not use the install program: you
    must register the shell integration DLL
    (<filename>ShellExtension*.dll</filename>) separately.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Installing shell integration requires Administrator user
      privileges.</para>
    </note>

    <para>First, uninstall the current shell integration version by running
    <filename>unregister.bat</filename> from the WinMerge directory. Then
    restart the computer so that Windows completes the uninstall.</para>

    <para>To register the shell integration DLL
    (<filename>ShellExtension*.dll</filename>), run
    <filename>register.bat</filename> from the WinMerge directory. We recommend
    that you restart the computer after installing shell integration, so that
    Windows updates all its references.</para>

    <section>
      <title>64-bit shell integration</title>

      <para>Starting with Version 2.6, WinMerge supports 64-bit Windows versions
      by including 64-bit shell integration. The WinMerge installer recognizes
      64-bit versions of Windows and can install the correct shell integration
      version.</para>

      <para>When you install shell integration manually from an archive file,
      the shell integration DLL is named
      <filename>ShellExtensionX64.dll</filename>. You can register and
      unregister this file by using <filename>register.bat</filename> and
      <filename>unregister.bat</filename>, as with 32-bit versions.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><indexterm>
        <primary>installing archive support</primary>
      </indexterm>7-Zip and archive support</title>

    <para>WinMerge uses <ulink url="http://www.7-zip.org/">7-Zip</ulink> for
    archive support, but the WinMerge installer does not install 7-Zip or
    archive support. Installing the 7-Zip application is recommended but not
    required for archive support. The 7-Zip installer is available for
    downloading from <ulink
    url="http://www.7-zip.org/">7-Zip.org</ulink>.</para>

    <important>
      <para>There are 7-Zip MSI installers that do not install all the files
      WinMerge needs (specifically, <filename>7zip_pad.xml</filename> in the
      7-Zip program folder). If there are problems with archive support
      enabling, try running the EXE version of the 7-Zip installer.</para>
    </important>

    <para>To install archive support, download and install the7-Zip plugin from
    <ulink url="http://winmerge.org/">WinMerge.org</ulink>, as described in the
    <xref linkend="Install_merge7zinstaller" /> section of this topic.</para>

    <para>WinMerge automatically detects an installed 7-zip in the system, so no
    configuration is needed.</para>

    <para>7-zip integration needs a compatible <filename>Merge7z*.dll</filename>
    file in the WinMerge program directory, where <filename>*</filename> is the
    7-Zip version installed. For example, 7-Zip version 4.42 requires
    <filename>Merge7z442.dll</filename>. And if
    <filename>WinMergeU.exe</filename> (the Unicode version) is used, then
    <literal><filename>U</filename></literal> is also added to filename, as in:
    <filename>Merge7z442U.dll</filename>. If the required DLL file is missing
    for any reason, you can copy it to the WinMerge directory, for example from
    the <filename>7z-Plugin</filename> archive that is available from the
    WinMerge download page.</para>

    <para>If the <filename>Merge7z*.dll</filename> file is missing, WinMerge
    displays a message that includes the name of the missing file and the
    recommended version of 7-Zip. You can also display this message by clicking
    <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Help</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Archive Support Disabled</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.</para>

    <section id="Install_merge7zinstaller">
      <title>Merge7zInstaller</title>

      <para><filename>Merge7zInstaller</filename> is a stand-alone installer for
      7-Zip integration.</para>

      <para>Installer file names may seem strange at first, but there is reason
      for them: they show the supported versions. The file name is formatted
      as</para>

      <para><synopsis>Merge7zInstaller<replaceable>XXX-YYY-ZZZ</replaceable>.exe</synopsis></para>

      <para>where <replaceable>XXX</replaceable> is the build number,
      <replaceable>YYY</replaceable> is the earliest 7-Zip version supported,
      and <replaceable>ZZZ</replaceable> is the latest 7-Zip version
      supported.</para>

      <para>For example, <filename>Merge7zInstaller0014-311-426.exe</filename>
      means build version 14, support for 7-Zip versions 3.11 to 4.26.</para>

      <para>This separate installer is much more flexible, because we can update
      it whenever 7-Zip is updated, and we don't add files to the base installer
      that users don't need.</para>

      <para>The latest version is always available at <ulink
      url="https://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=13216&amp;package_id=143957"
      userlevel="">7-Zip plugin</ulink> in our download page at SourceForge.net,
      and of course from our home page at <ulink
      url="http://winmerge.org/">WinMerge.org</ulink>.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>If you want to know immediately when we release new versions, you
        can monitor our releases. You are then notified through e-mail of new
        releases when they happen.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>Running the <filename>Merge7zInstaller</filename> is simple:</para>

      <para><orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Start the installer executable.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select the installation type and the DLL files (supported
            7-zip versions) to install:</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Shared installation</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Copies the 7-Zip plugin files to the system directory so
                  they can be shared between multiple WinMerge installations and
                  other programs using the 7-zip plugin. This is the recommended
                  installation.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Application specific installation</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Copies the 7-zip plugin files to the program directory.
                  Files are then usable only by that program.</para>

                  <para>When you choose this option, you must select the
                  executable in the directory where the plugin files are
                  installed. Select the WinMerge executable file when installing
                  to the WinMerge directory.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Enable standalone operation</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Also installs the required 7-Zip files to the program's
                  application-specific installation directory. This allows the
                  minimal usable installation of 7-Zip for archive support. You
                  can use this option when the 7-Zip application is not wanted
                  or needed.</para>

                  <para>This installation type contains only the files needed
                  for WinMerge (or other application) to enable archive support.
                  It does not install the 7-Zip user interface or other related
                  tools or files. After this installation it is not possible to
                  open or create 7-Zip archive files outside of WinMerge.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
