<sect1 id="Plugins">
  <title>Plugins</title>
  <para>Plugins are extra-features for WinMerge. They are not included in the basic version because they interest few users, or because they do not fit in WinMerge architecture.</para>
  <para>Each plugin:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>is a single file, either a dll or a scriptlet (extension <filename class="extension">.sct</filename>)</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>is installed in the subfolder <filename class="directory">MergePlugins</filename></simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>is easy to install: copy the plugin file in <filename class="directory">MergePlugins</filename>, close WinMerge if it is running, and launch it again</simpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <sect2>
    <title>Three categories of plugins</title>
    <para>"<guilabel>Plugins</guilabel>" is a generic name for extra-feature dll or scriptlets. Plugins features are spread over three categories:</para>
    <sect3>
      <title>Editor complement</title>
      <para>Operate custom operations on the currently selected text from the active editor pane.</para>
      <para>Example plugin: <filename>editor addin.sct</filename> (Turn the selection to UPPERCASE or lowercase.)</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Unpacker - Transform a file to a text format</title>
      <para>The plugin transform a file in a viewable format (for example, decompress a file).
      The original file is not changed. A temporary transformed file is created and loaded in WinMerge.</para>
      <para>Sometimes the transformed file can be packed back. (See the plugin details to know if it supports packing back.)
      Then you may merge and save the transformed file. The packing is done automatically in this case. To avoid problems,
      you are proposed to change the filename when saving a changed file.</para>
      <note>
        <para>When you compare folders, WinMerge doesn't need to display the files, but the diffing process can give a different result
        when you compare compressed and not compressed files (for example, uncompressed files may be identical, but the compressed files
        may differ if they include the date of creation). WinMerge applies the unpacker in all situations, and you are sure to have the
        same result when you compare folder, or when you merge two versions of a file.</para>
      </note>
      <para>Example plugin: <filename>DisplayXMLFiles.dll</filename> (Display XML files nicely, by consistently inserting tabs and linebreaks.)</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Prediffer - Preprocess files to hide some differences</title>
      <para>The plugin is not apply to the files displayed in the editor. It is applied only to temporary copies of the files, and this copies are then scanned to create the difference list.</para>
      <para>Example plugin: <filename>IgnoreColumns.dll</filename> (Ignore the differences inside given columns, while displaying the characters in these columns.)</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Select and apply a plugin</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>"<guilabel>Suggested plugin</guilabel>" and "<guilabel>Automatic mode</guilabel>"</title>
      <para>Each plugin specifies a list of file extensions (see plugins details for more info). When the file extension, either from
      the left or from the right file, matches the plugin list, the plugin is called "<guilabel>a suggested plugin</guilabel>".</para>
      <para>When "<guilabel>Automatic mode</guilabel>" is on, WinMerge searches for a suggested plugin and applies it if it is avaialble.
      When two suggested plugins are available for a file, WinMerge applies the first one only (alphabetical order).</para>
      <note>
        <para>"<guimenuitem>Automatic Unpacking</guimenuitem>" and "<guimenuitem>Auto prediffer</guimenuitem>" are two separate options. There is no option for editor complements.</para>
      </note>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Editor complement in folder view</title>
      <para><emphasis>Not available</emphasis></para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Editor complement in editor view</title>
      <para>Access list from <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guisubmenu>Scripts</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the main menu.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Unpacker in folder view</title>
      <para>Check <menuchoice><guimenu>Plugins</guimenu><guimenuitem>Automatic Unpacking</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the main menu.
      You need to update the results (<keycap>F5</keycap>). Each file is loaded again with its suggested unpacker and compared.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Unpacker in editor view</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open dialog: Select the two files first and then press the <guibutton>Select</guibutton> button right from the field "<guilabel>Unpacker</guilabel>".
          WinMerge displays the standard dialog for unpacker selection. Use the top combobox to select the plugin. Two generic choices "<guilabel>None</guilabel>"
          and "<guilabel>Automatic</guilabel>" are  also available.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the folder view when <menuchoice><guimenu>Plugins</guimenu><guimenuitem>Automatic Unpacking</guimenuitem></menuchoice> is checked:
          Just double click to open the file. The suggested plugin used during the folder comparison is used to load the file in the editor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the folder view, always: Select one file, then main menu <menuchoice><guimenu>Plugins</guimenu><guimenuitem>Edit with Unpacker</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
          WinMerge displays the dialog for unpacker selection. Select an unpacker and press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, WinMerge opens the editor view and applies this unpacker
          to load the file. This plugin is forgotten when you close the editor view.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Prediffer in folder view</title>
      <para>When the files are selected, right-click to open the context menu. Follow <menuchoice><guimenu>Plugin Settings</guimenu><guisubmenu>Prediffer Settings</guisubmenu></menuchoice>
      and select "<guimenuitem>Auto prediffer</guimenuitem>" or "<guimenuitem>No prediffer</guimenuitem>". Refresh the view (<keycap>F5</keycap>) to update the results.</para>
      <note>
        <para>"<guimenuitem>Auto prediffer</guimenuitem>" is a per-file option. Some files in the same folder can be in mode "<guimenuitem>No prediffer</guimenuitem>" and
        some in mode "<guimenuitem>Auto prediffer</guimenuitem>". When you change folder during a non-recursive compare, the mode is always reset to "<guimenuitem>No prediffer</guimenuitem>".</para>
      </note>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Prediffer in editor view</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the folder view when "<guimenuitem>Auto prediffer</guimenuitem>" is checked for a file: Just double click to open the file.
          The plugin used during the folder comparison is used in the editor before the diff algorithm.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>During an editor session, access prediffer lists with menu <menuchoice><guimenu>Plugins</guimenu><guisubmenu>Prediffer</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>:
          The active prediffer is checked. Suggested plugins are indicated first above the not-suggested ones. The files are compared again after the selection, you don't need to rescan.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Plugin details</title>
    <para>A file <filename>Plugins.txt</filename> is created during the setup process. It documents each installed plugin with the name and a quick description.
    If you don't use installer <filename>Plugins.txt</filename> is found from <filename class="directory">MergePlugins</filename> subfolder.</para>
    <para>Developers may find information and code of examples in the source package, under the folder "<filename class="directory">Plugins</filename>".</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Requirements</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>Windows Script Host</title>
      <para>Some editor complements need this optional component from Microsoft.</para>
      <para>If the list of editor complements does not present all editor plugins, this component is probably missing.
      You can check easily. WinMerge informs you with a comment at the bottom of the list. You may install WSH on any
      version of Windows (need IE 4.0). Download it from <ulink url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/downloads/list/webdev.asp">MSDN Library</ulink>.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Visual Basic runtime library</title>
      <para>Some plugins require Visual Basic runtime library to work.</para>
      <para>You can download the required file <filename><ulink url="http://www.dll-files.com/dllindex/dll-files.shtml?msvbvm60">msvbvm60.dll</ulink></filename>
      or use the <ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?familyid=7b9ba261-7a9c-43e7-9117-f673077ffb3c">Run-Time Redistribution Pack</ulink>
      from Microsoft. If you don't need the plugin, you can safely remove it.</para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
