<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="QuickStart">
  <title>Quick Start</title>

  <sect2>
    <title>Opening Files and Folders</title>

    <para>Start <productname>WinMerge</productname> and either select
    <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>File</guimenu>-menu, or
    click the yellow folder icon on the toolbar, or press <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>

        <keycap>O</keycap>
      </keycombo>. The file/folder selection dialog opens:</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="screenshots/OpenDlg1.gif" format="GIF" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>Two topmost fields in Open dialog are for selecting
    files/directories to compare. Comparison objects can be specified in one
    of four ways:</para>

    <para><orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter the path names directly into the edit fields</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button and use the
          file chooser to navigate to the desired object</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Expand the combo box and select a previously entered path
          (WinMerge remembers the last 20)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Drag &amp; drop something into the edit field from
          Explorer</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <para>Folder can be selected from Windows Open dialog (opens when
    <guibutton>Browse</guibutton>-button is selected) by browsing into folder
    and selecting <guibutton>Open</guibutton>-button. It does not require
    selecting a file. When <guilabel>Filename</guilabel> field in Windows Open
    dialog contains text "<guilabel>Directory Selection</guilabel>" selecting
    <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button selects currently visible folder. Open
    dialog always shows backslash "\" at end of folder name.</para>

    <para><note>
        <para>There can be only file &amp; file or folder &amp; folder
        selected to open for compare. If there is file &amp; folder or other
        one of files/folders cannot be found WinMerge disables
        <guibutton>OK</guibutton>-button in dialog.</para>
      </note></para>

    <para><guilabel>Filter</guilabel> field can be used to select files by
    extension to compare. Default value is "*.*" which includes all files. But
    listing one or more extensions restricts compare to only files with those
    extensions. Multiple extensions are separated with space or semicolon. For
    example, entering the file filter <filename>*.cpp;*.hpp;*.c;*.h</filename>
    will cause WinMerge to ignore all files except C and C++ source
    files.</para>

    <para>File filters are a much more powerful way (than extension filters)
    to select files and folders. Use the <guibutton>Select</guibutton> button
    next to the <guilabel>Filters</guilabel> field to see a list of available
    filters, and to choose a file filter to use.</para>

    <para>If the <guilabel>Include Subfolders</guilabel> checkbox is checked
    then WinMerge compares all subfolders and shows all files and folders it
    finds in one view. Otherwise only the current folder is compared, and
    subfolders are listed by name (without their contents), so the user can
    browse into them.</para>

    <para>Unpacker selection is for plugins.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>Status of currently selected files or directories is shown with
      text in bottom of the dialog. If one of the paths is invalid this text
      tells which one it is.</para>
    </tip>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Comparing Folders</title>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="screenshots/dircomp1.gif" format="GIF" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>If two folders were selected in the Open dialog then the folder
    compare window is opened. Folder compare shows list of files and
    subfolders found by WinMerge. Using <guimenu>Merge</guimenu> menu items,
    toolbar items, or context menu items, files and folders can be managed in
    many ways.</para>

    <para>If the selected file exists in both sides (and it is not a binary
    file) it can be opened to file compare. File can be opened by:<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>selecting <guimenuitem>Compare</guimenuitem> from
          <guimenu>Merge</guimenu> menu</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>selecting <guimenuitem>Compare</guimenuitem> from context
          menu</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>double-clicking with mouse</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>pressing <keycap>Enter</keycap> key</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <para>After file compare is closed file's status is updated to folder
    compare.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Comparing Files</title>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="screenshots/filecomp1.gif" format="GIF" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>File compare shows two files side by side. Different lines are
    highlighted with background color. One or more consecutive different lines
    form one difference (or "diff"). WinMerge mostly works with these
    differences, not separate lines.</para>

    <para><important>
        <para>Notice how WinMerge fills missing lines in other side. Similar
        lines are always side by side. This is different from most other
        compare/merge programs and can take a while to learn.</para>
      </important>With merging commands (in <guimenu>Merge</guimenu> menu)
    lines in difference can be copied between sides. Missing lines can be
    copied also. When missing lines are copied from one side to another,
    matching existing lines are removed. In the above screenshot, copying
    lines in second difference from the left to the right would remove
    matching lines from the left side.</para>

    <para>WinMerge has an simple integrated editor. Typing, copying, cutting
    and pasting text works. If <guilabel>Automatic rescan</guilabel> is
    enabled then WinMerge updates file differences while files are edited. If
    <guilabel>Automatic rescan</guilabel> is disabled files can be updated
    selecting <guimenuitem>Refresh</guimenuitem> from
    <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>-menu, clicking toolbar button with two yellow
    arrows or pressing <keycap>F5</keycap> key.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
