<sect1 id="Whatsnew22">
  <title>What's new in 2.2</title>
  <sect2>
    <title>Unicode support</title>
    <para>WinMerge 2.2 is distributed with ANSI executable (WinMerge.exe) for Windows 95/98/ME and Unicode executable (WinMergeU.exe) for Windows NT /200/XP. Unicode executable supports UCS-2 and UTF-8 files and filenames.</para>
    <note>
      <para>It is unfortunate that two executable files are needed. But there is no currently way to get only one executable working. MS Unicode layer does not help WinMerge since WinMerge needs to be comparing files in different codepages.</para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Archive support</title>
    <para>WinMerge 2.2 can open and save several archivetypes. Archive support requires installing 7-zip. Refer to Read Me.rtf file for info about compatible 7-zip version. 7-zip can be downloaded from <ulink url="http://www.7-zip.org/">http://www.7-zip.org/</ulink></para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Shell integration</title>
    <para>WinMerge 2.2 can be integrated into Windows Shell. Shell integration adds "Winmerge" menuitem to Windows Explorer's context menu for easy and fast comparing files and directories.</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Selecting filter from commandline</title>
    <para>New -f commandline switch allows selecting used filter or mask for files.</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Project files</title>
    <para>WinMerge can read paths to open from project files. Project files are simple XML files storing one or two paths, possibly filter and subfolder iclusion too.</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Generating patches</title>
    <para>GNU/diffutils compatible patch files can be created from two files. Several formats and compare options are supported.</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Plugins</title>
    <para>Plugins are now supported to preprocess files before actual compare or to extend editor functionality. Plugins can be programmed using several languages supporting COM. Example plugins are included.</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Improved directory compare</title>
    <para>Many new features and improvements:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>More columns added (e.g. file sizes and attributes), shown columns can be selected and reordered.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Filtered items have now own category (Skipped) and icons. Filtered items can be set to hidden/visible from View-menu.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Floating statusbar during compare process, compare can be stopped and files/dirs compared so far are shown</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Newer file/directory is indicated with asterisk (*) in date field</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>One or both directories can be set read-only, preventing accidental overwriting.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Selected items count is shown in statusbar.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Improved file compare</title>
    <para>Many new features and improvements:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Rewritten undo/redo code</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed "Ignore blank lines" feature</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enchanged EOL handling (files can contain different EOL styles in one file)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Linenumber, current column and char, line length and char count shown in statusbar</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>One ot both files can be set read-only to prevent accidental edits</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Copy difference to left/right and advance to next makes merging faster</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Diff pane to show current difference in two vertical panes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Highlight word differences in lines</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Merge-mode (or 1.7 mode) to navigate and merge differences easier and faster.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Goto -dialog for moving fast to certain line or difference.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Location pane showing overall picture from files and allowing moving to location by double-clicking.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Moved lines detection. Moved lines can be shown with different color in file area and location pane.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>More color options. Text color, missing line colors and moved line colors can be configured.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
